Danish, Max D. Collected Documents. 6036/013
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Danish, Max D. Collected Documents.
1946-1964
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Danish, Max D.
6036/013
1.5 cubic feet
1.5 linear ft.
Articles, reprints, pamphlets, correspondence, photographs.
This collection includes play scripts and other writings by Max Danish, as well as notes and collected documents about the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union.
5767195
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, October 05, 2011
EAD encoding:
Kathryn Dowgiewicz, January 10, 2013
Biographical / Historical
Founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States, the ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. In 1995, the ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) to form the Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE).
Biographical / Historical
Max D. Danish, born in 1887 in Vitebsk, Russia, immigrated to the United States at the age of 14 and began work in the garment industry. He was involved with the early struggles and strikes of the union, and provided publicity for the union during the Cloakmakers' strike in 1910. Danish worked on a daily newspaper in Connecticut and went to New York University to study journalism and received a law degree. In 1914, he became the managing editor of the official ILGWU publication, the "Ladies' Garment Worker," and director of press relations. When the ILGWU publication became "Justice" in 1919, Danish took over as editor, helming the publication until his retirement in 1951. Danish also served the union as director of publicity and attempted to change the impression of union news, creating a paper that had more general interest. Through his positions with publicity and publications for the union, Danish strived to change the attitude of the press toward union news. Danish wrote the biographies "William Green: A Pictorial Biography" and "The World of David Dubinsky." With close to four decades of service to the ILGWU, Danish was a reporter, editor, public relations expert and historian. He died on January 11, 1964 at the age of 77.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains manuscripts, plays and drafts of original material by Max D. Danish. Many are fiction and focus on the fashion and garment industry, including "57th Street" and a similar version entitled "Pirates on 5th Avenue," "Dresses, Unlimited," a play in three acts from 1940, and "Inside Dresses or Town and Gown: A Play in Three Acts," a precursor to "Dresses, Unlimited," and "Mr. Lewis and Mr. Green," a conversation between John Lewis and William Green in verse. Also included is a manuscript for the "History of the ILGWU." The collection has numerous rough drafts, ideas for stories, speeches and articles, items both typed and handwritten. Available is collected material on historical information, newspaper clippings, and articles on David Dubinsky.
The collection contains biographical material on Max Danish, including clippings from his retirement from the union in 1951, his brief stint as an AFL news southern correspondent in Miami in 1954, articles written by Danish in "The New Leader" (paper devoted to Socialist and labor movements), and the clippings of the many letters and opinions he wrote to various newspapers regarding labor matters.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records 5780/070: ILGWU. Ladies' Garment Worker 5780/051 mf: ILGWU. Justice. Microfilm.
Danish, Max D.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union -- Archives.
5767195
- 57th Street (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Dresses, Unlimited, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Dresses, Unlimited, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Dresses, Unlimited, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Scope and Contents
  Draft
- Inside Dresses or Town and Gown (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Mr. Lewis and Mr. Green (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Pirates on 5th Avenue (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Pirates on 5th Avenue (Box 1, Folder 8)
- A Superwife Returns (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Manuscript, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Correspondence, speeches, notes
- [Writings and research, folder 1 of 4] (Box 1, Folder 11)
- [Writings and research, folder 2 of 4] (Box 2, Folder 1)
- [Writings and research, folder 3 of 4] (Box 2, Folder 2)
- [Writings and research, folder 4 of 4] (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Articles, correspondence to New Leader, 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Cut-outs from original manuscript, World of David Dubinsky (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Retirement, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Clippings
- Miami Beach, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Hearst Press, Westbrook Pegler, anti-David Dubinsky, 1949-1952 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Stolberg's book (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Irwin Ross, 11 articles, New York Post, Life of David Dubinsky, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Max Danish death, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Letters to Mrs. Danish
- Newspaper clippings, 1948-1961 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- AFL-CIO merger, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- World of David Dubinsky, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Protocol, Philosophy and Practice, Hoffman (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Rosenberg's memoirs (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Palestine, 1944-1952 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Southern drive, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- History of the ILGWU [folder 1 of 3] (Box 3, Folder 1)
- History of the ILGWU [folder 2 of 3] (Box 3, Folder 2)
- History of the ILGWU [folder 3 of 3] (Box 3, Folder 3)